[Music]
based on how we evolve the optimum
dietary potassium intake likely greatly
exceeds current and even recommended
intakes
the problem is we replace many of the
potassium-rich plant foods we used to
stuff our faces with like fruits leafy
greens and other vegetables including
roots and tubers with calorie dense junk
stripped not only a fiber but also
potassium such as you know added fats
and sugars so when a traditional largely
plant-based diet potassium content is
high sodium content is low but now high
blood pressure is the second leading
cause of death in the world killing more
than 10 million people a year second
only to unhealthy diets the number one
killer of humanity we can improve both
by eating more whole healthy plant foods
like beans and greens which are packed
with potassium which lowers blood
pressure
but since most of us are getting too
much sodium along with too little
potassium what about using salt
substitutes after all the most commonly
used salt substitute is potassium
chloride she would be swapping out
sodium for potassium
and it works based on a meta-analysis of
more than a dozen randomized control
trials replacing sodium chloride with
potassium chloride lowers blood pressure
and most of the trials involved just
swapping out regular salt for less than
30 potassium chloride and they still got
results and at less than 30 most people
can't even tell the difference between
regular salt and the potassium salt
so it can taste exactly the same and
drop your blood pressures what's the
catch
potassium chloride is generally
considered as safe by the fda with the
only major concern for healthy people
being that if you go completely 100
sodium free and use straight potassium
chloride like all these it can taste
kind of funny adding a bitter or
metallic taste
i've found that it depends on what i'm
seasoning with it it works perfectly
well on some things but makes other
things completely inedible
when i learned about the sodium science
and threw out my salt shaker for good
within a few weeks my palate totally
changed and everything tasted fine
without salt except pesto for some
reason pesto without salt just never
tasted like it used to to me so i so i
tried the potassium chloride salt
substitute and it worked perfectly i
couldn't tell the difference at all so i
had the best of both worlds
then i remembered how as a kid i used to
put a tiny sprinkle of salt on
watermelon like they do in the south to
make it even sweeter so i tried it with
potassium salt
and almost gagged
so it's definitely not for everything
the reason healthy people don't have to
worry about getting too much potassium
is that our kidneys just pee out the
excess
okay but that's with potassium and food
what about supplements no adverse
effects have been shown for long-term
intakes and potassium supplements as
high as 3 000 milligrams a day in fact
blood levels of potassium are maintained
in the normal range by healthy kidneys
even when potassium intake is increased
to approximately 15 000 milligrams a day
which is no surprise since we evolved
eating so many healthy plant foods so
many fruits and vegetables that the
normal natural potassium intake for the
human species may be on the order of 15
000 milligrams a day
basically
the normal range for potassium levels in
the blood is between 3.5 and 5. and you
start to worry when it starts creeping
up towards six but give people potassium
supplements like all the salt
substitution trials they've been giving
study subjects an average of about 2 000
milligrams of potassium a day and blood
levels only go up
0.14 so they might go up from 4 to 4.14
not something that would push you into
trouble
now there's a limit if you have a
quote-unquote massive banana eating
habit you could bump your potassium from
normal to above six but that was
evidently from years of not eating much
of anything except up to 20 bananas a
day eating 10 pounds of carrots every
day is also probably not a good idea
that's like 75 carrots in one day
which you could only do with a juicer
which is what this person attempted to
do as part of a quack cancer cure
what about overdoing salt substitutes
this report from the 1940s was on
lithium poisoning from the use of salt
substitutes why because lithium chloride
was used as a salt substitute jesus
but what about potassium chloride which
is what's used today there is one fatal
case of someone who committed suicide by
downing a little more than a tablespoon
of potassium chloride salt substitute
that doesn't seem like a lot just a
tablespoon i mean how can we keep that
on the shell as if only a tablespoon
will kill you
well even less than that of regular salt
taken at once can kill you too in fact
saltwater ingestion was evidently a
traditional method of suicide in ancient
china though these days one may be more
likely to die that way from abusive
religious practices
having said all that there are a small
number of the population who may run
into problems primarily those with
severely impaired kidney function
that's why there's been such a
reluctance to push potassium-based salt
substitutes on a population level if
your kidneys can't regulate your
potassium then you can definitely run
into a serious issue and we're talking
about folks with known kidney disease
diabetes since diabetes can lead to
kidney damage severe heart failure those
on medications that impair potassium
excretion older adults and individuals
with adrenal insufficiency if you aren't
sure if you're at risk ask your doctor
about getting your kidney function
tested
ironically potassium is so good at
reducing deaths from high blood pressure
even among those with kidney disease
using potassium chloride salt
substitutes would probably still save
more lives despite the risk
traditional dietary recommendations to
kidney patients limited the intake of
fruits and vegetables because of their
high potassium content however this
paradigm is rapidly changing due to the
multiple benefits derived from a
fundamentally plant-based diet a whole
food plant-based diet may even
ameliorate chronic kidney disease
there's increasing evidence that a whole
food plant-based diet may offer benefits
like slowing the progression of chronic
kidney disease and delaying kidney
failure
so the practice of restricting dietary
potassium in kidney patients should
really be reserved for patients with
documented hyperkalemia a potassium
level of six or higher because the key
to halting the progression of chronic
kidney disease may in fact lie
in the produce aisle
[Music]
you